Guide to the William L. Ford and Carl August Linn papers 1900-1920
Montana Historical Society Research Center
William L. Ford and Carl August Linn papers
1900-1920
Montana Historical Society Archives
MC 193
Ford, William L., 1878-1940
William Ford was a White Sulphur Springs, Montana lawyer and Meagher County attorney. Carl Linn joined Ford's law office in 1912, and was elected Meagher County attorney the same year. The collection (1900-1920, 1948, undated) contains correspondence, subject files, and miscellany.
1 linear ft
Biographical Note
William L. Ford graduated from the University of Michigan law school in 1900 and began practicing law in White Sulphur Springs, Montana, in the same year. In 1904, he ran for Meagher County attorney and was defeated by N.B. Smith. In 1905, he became the city attorney and clerk, and in 1906 was elected county attorney, a position he held through 1912. He decided not to run for re-election in November of that year due to his father's illness. He devoted his time to running his father's ranch near White Sulphur Springs, and by 1913 had formed a partnership with Richard Manger. In 1918 or 1919 Ford renewed his law practice. He was elected district judge as a Republican in 1920. He had been active in the Masons and the Republican Party before his election, having been appointed county chairman of the Roosevelt Memorial Association in 1919 and chairman of the Republican Ways and Means Committee for Meagher County in 1920. William Ford married Margaret Young on December 25, 1907.
Carl August Linn joined William Ford's law office in March 1912. While retaining the name of "Ford and Linn," Linn began operating as the firm's sole attorney when Ford turned his attention to ranching in 1912. Linn was elected county attorney in November 1912.
Ford and Linn acted as collection agents for out-of-state and in-state firms and individuals. They also handled cases involving property disputes, water rights, sales of horses, claims involving the Montana Railroad Company and the Northern Pacific Railroad, divorce, probate, assault, etc., and collected rents for out-of-town landlords.
The collection includes general correspondence (1900-192O, undated), subject files (1948, undated), and miscellany (1917-1919).
The collection consists almost entirely of the outgoing and incoming correspondence, arranged chronologically, of William L. Ford and Carl August Linn in their capacity as private attorneys. There is some correspondence directed to them, and to which they responded, as county attorneys. Also included in the correspondence are a few incoming letters (1904) to Max Waterman (Ford's predecessor as county attorney) and from Ford's brother Arthur and his sister Ida. The rest of the correspondence is from clients, other attorneys, judges, the Montana attorney general, and landlords whose properties Ford and Linn handled.
The subject file concerns the Meagher County Health Council, an organization established by the Meagher County Planning Board to persuade a physician and dentist to take up practice in Meagher County, sponsor a health clinic, sponsor health education programs, etc.
The miscellany consists of William Ford's Mason membership cards and a receipt for Ford's attorney annual license tax.
This collection is arranged into three series: 1) General Correspondence, 2) Subject Files, and 3) Miscellany.
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
An unidentified inventory of household goods and personal effects (1936-1941) has been transferred to the Museum. See below for more information.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Ford, William L., 1878-1940; Linn, Carl August, 1884-1942
Meagher County (Mont.)--Medical care; Meagher County (Mont.)--Politics and government; White Sulphur Springs (Mont.); White Sulphur Springs (Mont.)--Commerce
Chinese--Montana; County attorneys--Montana; Divorce--Montana; Japanese--Montana; School bonds--Montana; Water rights--Montana
Montana; Civil Procedure and Courts
Lawyers--Montana
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- General Correspondence
  - Chronological (includes claims against the Montana Railway Company), 1900-1904 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Chronological (includes claims against the Montana Railway Company, redistricting of judicial districts, water rights, etc.), 1905, 1907 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - Chronological (includes attack on Japanese Great Northern Railway Company worker, attack on a Chinese restaurant worker in Harlowton, etc.), 1908-1909 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - Chronological (includes school bonds, divorce, saloon leases, Japanese robber, etc.), 1909-1910 (Box-folder 1 / 4-5)
  - Chronological (includes divorce, school bonds, etc.), 1911 (Box-folder 1 / 6-7)
  - Chronological (includes school bonds, Republican politics, divorce, water rights, etc.), 1912 (Box-folder 2 / 1-4)
  - Chronological (includes school bonds,judicial districts, school elections, divorce, etc.), 1913 (Box-folder 2 / 5-7)
  - Chronological (includes school bonds, etc.), 1914 (Box-folder 3 / 1-2)
  - Chronological (includes divorce, etc.), 1915 (Box-folder 3 / 3-4)
  - Chronological, 1916 (Box-folder 3 / 5)
  - Chronological (includes Republican politics, divorce, etc.), 1917-1919 (Box-folder 3 / 6)
  - Chronological (includes Republican politics, etc.), 1920 (Box-folder 3 / 7)
- Subject Files
  - Meagher County Health Council, 1948, undated (Box-folder 3 / 8)
- Miscellany
  - List of artifacts transferred to the Museum, undated (Box-folder 3 / 9)
  - William L. Ford's Masonic membership cards and receipt for annual attorney license tax, 1917-1919 (Box-folder 3 / 10)